[Music]
hello everybody good evening good day to
all of you and welcome to the latest
episode of the ask a budget show it is
great to be back online
with you all and let us see who all is
there with us today
i can see kabir anish priyanshi akshit
crazy brain pretty vladimir additional
and a whole lot of other people good
evening good day to all of you and thank
you so much for being on the show with
me
this fine evening over here
uh so with that said shall we get right
into the questions let's do that let's
get into the questions what do we have
for today
what the questions do we have
question number one
ah this question
says sir course
abhi says
very interested i want to know
the course is paid or free
uh could you please speak about the
planned course on history departing says
five hours or less but anyway all that
yeah okay so what is this course about
yes like i have announced on the
community tab of this channel i am
launching a course on indian history
i am launching it tomorrow if everything
goes well if all the technical stuff is
right my team is working on that so i am
launching the course tomorrow right so
when is the course coming it's coming
tomorrow is it paid or free it's a paid
course right it's it's going to be a
paid course it's not i'm not going to be
a free course um
so what is this course about it's about
the overall uh
length and breadth of indian history
it's focusing is going to focus more on
ancient indian history is going to focus
more on those parts of india's history
that uh
that are not typically spoken about in
in textbooks and in courses and all that
in in academia so i'm going to focus
more on ancient indian history less on
the independent struggle in the past
1000 years of humiliation which
everybody has
read about so many times in our
textbooks i'm going to focus more on the
ancient history and the parts of history
that we don't really know much about
so much of this stuff that i'm gonna be
speaking about in the course i have
already covered over here yes but what's
different about the course first of all
it's gonna be chronological it'll start
the the logical beginning and it's going
to cover some things that i have not
spoken about here because in the ask a
budget show i answer questions but there
are questions that people have never
asked me and therefore i have not spoken
about those things so i'm going to be
covering all those aspects in a
chronological fashion uh
deepali says five hours or less it's
gonna be roughly five hours beginning to
start off with but i'm gonna be adding
more stuff so eventually after a couple
of weeks it may end up being double that
size yeah double that length so what i'm
releasing tomorrow is just the initial
uh
phase of the course i'm gonna you will
you will witness me building it
as as time goes by
as the couple as the next one or two
weeks go by i'm gonna be adding more
stuff to it so you're gonna see me
create the course in real time
essentially add to it in real time but
yeah tomorrow you get the uh initial
installment or so of the course the
first big big uh
section of the course so it will release
tomorrow it's going to be a paid course
see it's like this i have already
everything i'm doing i'm not holding
anything back everything uh i speak
about over here is i'm giving all the
information i've been doing it for more
than one year the thing is this you get
something for free you don't value it
you don't value it it's just human
psychology it's human nature it applies
to me too you get something really nice
for free you don't really evaluate much
but if you pay something for it then
you're gonna
put some value on that so that's why
it's gonna be a paid course and it's i
had said it would be the price for pizza
i think it's gonna be a little more than
the price of a pizza a little more
valuable than that but not too much
right so uh once the course releases
tomorrow
as soon as it releases as soon as it
goes live i'm gonna put a
uh uh community post over here and maybe
i'll put a video as well right so
uh it comes tomorrow all right so those
of you who want to take it you can go
ahead and do that
all right
okay rajat says what's your take on the
boycott bollywood movement that's
happening nowadays considering movies
except the kashmir files getting
miserably flopped even before their
release should it continue to happen
um who am i to say whether it should
happen or not the people must decide
india is a democracy
it india is a democratic republic
right so the people get to decide the
people have the power to watch something
or not watch something it is entirely
the people's choice
if you
if there is
something that the people want they're
gonna go and take it
if there are movies that are being
released that they are interested in
they will go and watch those movies but
if really movies are being released that
people have no interest in then they
will not watch it i mean what's wrong
with that it's it's your choice it's
people's choice
and yeah some people are calling for
this
calling for a boycott of bollywood well
i think
one can kind of understand why why
people are so frustrated and angry with
bollywood i mean bollywood has been
consistently uh
putting out a certain kind of slant in
the movies cultural slant and
one could
say without without lying that bollywood
has consistently been hindu phobic so
most of the people eventually they will
they're going to see through it right
and then these things obviously there's
going to be reaction to it yeah so it's
up to bollywood what they want to do
if they want to see there is a demand
for certain kinds of entertainment
people are watching certain kinds of
movies nowadays people seem to be
watching movies that are being released
in the south of india right
so there is a demand for those kinds of
movies
so it's up to bollywood if they want to
survive they can make movies the kind of
movies that people do want to watch
instead of telling people what they what
they should watch
people are not gonna take that nonsense
anymore people will not
take kindly to be told what to think and
what to like and what to watch
people have options today that's a good
thing about having options it empowers
people
so um
i think what's happening is just
democracy in action
the people who say that we we we are all
about democracy we are anti-fascism and
all that well here's your democracy in
action be happy about it
right
so if you if you pro produce poor
quality movies if you produce movies
that are preachy and boring
and and if you lecture people and if you
tell people to uh
espouse a certain kind of ideology it's
not gonna work
it's not gonna work and the problem with
bollywood is the arrogance
they're they're like you know if you
don't want to watch it don't watch it
and then they afterwards they come
begging so that's the problem so uh
i have never
called for a boycott or anything but i
completely understand why people have
this sentiment right so it's not about
should it continue to happen or not
continuing to happen it's just what's
happening it's a natural reaction it's a
democratic reaction it's the people's
voice the people have spoken a couple of
movies have been released recently which
completely flopped well well deserved i
would say they made movies the kind they
could they made the kind of movies that
people don't want to watch that's simply
what it's telling you
the people did not want to watch that
movie
and the
yes so that's what it is the markets
will will
give you a message
based on whether they buy something or
not and clearly they're not buying it so
that's how it is now it's up to
bollywood the ball is in bollywood's
court are they gonna keep producing such
trashy movies that no one wants or will
they
learn the lesson
and and adapt
and otherwise there are plenty of
options that people have there's so many
different uh forms of entertainment that
people can consume these days so
bollywood is not that important it's no
longer that important or that relevant
so this is just evolution in process
natural selection in process
the free market is spoken
so yeah i think whatever is happening is
is is right
the people have the right
to watch or not watch something you
can't force them to buy tickets and go
and watch your stuff if they're not
interested so yeah good
it's good
all right
vinay man says what are your thoughts on
the five pledges by prime minister modi
on independence day can india really
become become a developed nation by 2047
and also what we as the youth of this
country can do to make india a developed
nation all right what are the pledges
let me take a look at the pledges um let
me google it up
what are the pledges that the prime
minister uh
took let's see let's put that on the
screen
the pledges
one second i think i have a news report
here
i don't want to subscribe sorry
all right here we are independence day
22 what are the five pledges listed by
pm modi for india at 100. so we have
just crossed 75 years after 1947 so
another 25 years and we will be at the
100 year mark so what are the pledges
number one making india a developed
nation by 2045.
modi said that every indian must resolve
to make india a developed nation by 2045
when india enters its hundredth year of
independence right
secondly removing all traces of
colonialism i really like to hear i like
to say this it's really great that he
has said this it's important for every
indian to rid himself or herself from
the vestiges of colonialism and slavery
in our actions and our mindset very
important
very important
vixit bharat develop india taking pride
in our roots and heritage indians are so
ashamed of their own culture and their
own roots it's so good to see the prime
minister say these things so good to say
this yeah
unity in integrity yeah well that's
something we need to work on there are
problems yes
and the sense of duty to among the
citizens yes citizens today are all
about my rights my rights i have the
right to do the i would like to do that
but what are you contributing to the
nation into society most people
contribute nothing but they demand
rights rights rights so that is
something people need to learn if you
want rights you also have duties that
you need to fulfill right so yes very
good
points the prime minister has made so
the question of vinai is asking is can
india really become a developed nation
by 2047
yes why not
uh 25 years is a whole lot of time
it certainly can happen if the light or
right leadership is play is in place and
the right actions are taken and
obviously everybody has to contribute
only the prime minister or only the
government doing things and everybody
else just sitting sitting on the back
sides doesn't work
everybody has to contribute so what can
we as a youth of the country do to make
india develop nation firstly
uh stop wasting time doing useless
things stop wasting your money on
useless things people waste their money
on things they don't need use the money
to to develop yourselves and develop the
nation invested in something
that sort of thing right raise your
standards stop this chalta attitude
right don't waste time time is limited
time is precious when you are 17 years
old you don't realize it yeah but one
day it all ends so make the best of the
time you have right cons build something
instead of consuming consuming consuming
and enjoying enjoying and doing create
something create something in a big way
or a small way in any small way even if
you contribute a little thing a little
bit of thing to the to the society it's
good you know you've you've done
something positive
so figure out how to contribute
something to society
a life is a useful life only when you
give more than you take
right
that's how it is think about all the
people that you think positively about
whom you feel warmly about maybe in the
nation maybe in the whole world maybe
around yourself in your immediate
neighborhood which are the people you
like and these are the people you feel
warmly about i can guarantee that the
the two or three people that you really
like and you feel warmly about are the
people who give more than they take
from everybody else so be that sort of
person stop wasting time stop wasting
money
don't
treat time as something that is
available in an infinite quantity
uh its time is extremely precious it's
even more pressure than money so that's
how it is so you need to raise your
standards please raise your standards
stop being complacent stop being having
this
attitude which is so endemic in india
right so if you do these things and we
all work together if we enough of us
change our standards and raise our
standards india will soon enough become
a developed nation hopefully by 2045 or
2047 right so that is what i can say in
a brief about this thing yes
okay arjun singh says could you please
comment on the unescorted access given
to the pentagon to the pentagon given by
the u.s to over indian defense uh
whatever
stash i don't know
whatever yeah okay um seems like a
pretty huge deal to me giving his access
access to the pentagon means u.s is
really willing to level up defense
cooperation with india and this will not
be limited to the indo-pacific strategy
maybe india the u.s wants us to give
them company as a global super cop i'm
pretty sure the next 25-30 years indian
army will be in a position to carry out
true peacekeeping operations around the
world
and not the hope that india has been
doing for the u.s has been doing for
decades
okay okay okay okay okay firstly let's
go to the bottom of this this question
and talk about this peacekeeping ops um
why should india carry out peacekeeping
operations why
simple question
why should a nation
carry out peacekeeping operations in
another place right now india is part of
the uni is part of the duty we have to
send some people and it gives them a
little bit of exposure and all but
overall this concept i don't like it
if there is
a lack of peace somewhere else why is it
my problem
why do i have to go and
do peacekeeping operations what do i get
out of it when i say i i mean my nation
why should india aspire to be a global
super cop
the u.s is not a global super cop the
u.s is a global thug please understand
the difference they pretend to be a cop
while being a thug
it's like a goon pretending to be a cop
wearing a nice uniform and then doing
whatever the hell they want that's what
the us is please understand the
difference why is it so so hard to see
what's really happening
right so i don't know why india should
aspire to be a global super cop and
carry out peacekeeping
peacekeeping operations what does india
get written for for that
india's resources india's manpower woman
power india's time
is all precious it should only be used
for the upliftment of india and the
progress of india that is how the
nation-state system works
borders do exist so that's number one
secondly uh unescorted access to the
pentagon
unescorted access to the pender you
think it it means anything whatsoever it
means nothing
it means they will open the corridor you
can wander around there that's all
they will not give access to any real
secrets or anything of any value
indians are so easy to fool
uh
i've read this somewhere yeah
okay i let me put this on the screen
please understand this the americans
understand indians very well nowadays
it's like this take a look
highly protocol conscious indians are
easily slighted and easily flattered
yeah
so that's what they have understood
about indians uh indians or indians have
this obsession with protocol
uh maybe it's because of british
traditions because we are so mentally
colonized that we have ingrained all the
british nonsense
and they think it's an ingrained
superiority complex it's actually an
inferiority complex whatever
so
indians are are extremely protocol
conscious you give them some stupid
symbolic gesture they become they they
go on top of the moon they feel like yes
they have been given due respect and all
that nonsense yeah so that's how it is
the americans understand this very well
and we can say this in action people
think this so-called symbolic access is
some game changer no my dear friends it
is not any kind of game changer it is
just a symbolic gesture a meaningless
gesture it does not bring anything to
the table for india what will india get
by wandering around in a corridor when
one or two government officers get to
wander in some corridor
we are not getting access to any
computer system any database
we're not getting access to any
technology that we don't have
none of these things is happening this
is just a meaningless symbolism gesture
and i'm sure the media must be tom
tomming it i don't watch news or media
anymore thankfully but yeah i'm sure
that sort of thing is happening and
that's why people are so easily uh
fooled and taken by this it means
absolutely nothing it is a pointless
symbolic meaningless gesture designed to
fool gullible people that's all it is it
gives
nothing
to india nothing whatsoever all right
please understand that
all right shubham says i recently
recently
president
okay let me
recently the sri lankan president
sri rani vikrama singh ji
stated that india
aspires to be an economic superpower and
if it happens it will be because of shri
panditji mr nehru ji what is my opinion
about this
what is my opinion about this you know
what my opinion is
i i am getting the feeling
i'm getting the feeling that shri
is just as magnificent magnificent a
personality
as the incredible shri nehru ji was
that's the feeling that i'm getting
yeah so mr
shree
vikrama sangaji is just that towering of
a statesman
and and a magnificent person just like
mr neruji was that's all i can say about
this
great man i'm sure mr vikramashi a great
man
okay saurabh says journalists embrace
the idea of free speech
just a couple of days ago however when
the ministry of power strongly reverted
the journals on twitter for
falsification of facts an entire
ecosystem went into condemning the act
and the ministry
was it appropriate and or justified for
a union ministry to do so
okay um interesting questions what's the
thing let's see if we have something on
the screen we can put something on the
screen do we have this ministry of power
ministry of
power
let us see oh yeah the first tweet
itself okay let's take a look and let's
put this on the screen what did the
ministry of power do
that we should be aware of
so this refers to the tweet of one
so-and-so person said to be a
correspondent of so-and-so place or
whatever the tweet displays
ignorance of the sector which she is
reported to be covering and then they go
on to give a detailed explanation of
what the facts are and how that lady has
been uh distorting the facts or whatever
right
that is what has happened and see i was
i did not really study this this
incident or whatever but yes it has come
to my attention that something like this
happened so the question is was it
appropriate for the ministry
to do so was it justified for the
minister to do so you know what is
india's national motto
india's national motto my dear friends
is satyameva
so if somebody does an asaphya kind of
thing should the government not correct
them and put the record straight
especially when the so-called journalist
is misleading the people
now the ministry of twitter handle has
gone ahead rebutted the lady and put out
the facts in great detail has any
journalist been able to prove them wrong
that you are wrong
no
has the lady been able to rebut them and
say and and uh demonstrate that they the
ministry is wrong and she's right no
it's not happened then why is it
unjustified or inappropriate for the
ministry to put the record straight to
set the records straight
when somebody is lying and misleading
the public should the government not put
the records right why is it
inappropriate why is it unjustified i
just don't get it
i'm glad for a change the ministry of
whatever power has taken a strong stand
in public typically the government
doesn't respond to these things you see
all kinds of malicious lies being spread
over the media over social media by
various journalists of various places
various organizations it happens all the
time
journalists
embrace
the idea of priest of free speech
as an exercise in virtue signaling but
what they do is the exact opposite most
journalists i'm not saying all of them
most journalists
a majority of journalists maybe five
percent may be really good and they may
be doing their duty
and and doing real journalism but i
would say about 90 95 percent are doing
the opposite of that they're they're
they're doing propaganda they're they're
peddling narratives and and agendas
and the ministry set the record straight
i don't see why
there's anything wrong with it
let the truth prevail right so uh i'm
sure the ecosystem must have gone into a
overdrive condemning the
ministry or whatever well have they been
able to prove the ministry wrong
if they have not been able to prove
prove the ministry wrong and what are
they talking about
so i'm glad this happened and this
should happen more often
these journalists who are peddling
agendas and narratives and misleading
the public need to be called out and
exposed i'm glad it's happened for a
change really good step
mr veteran says please explain the
history of sapiens in short what is
sapiens homo sapiens
i suppose it's homo sapiens um
the history of homo sapiens where do we
begin let's begin at the very beginning
13.8 billion years before today yeah
that's where the history of homo sapiens
begins so 13.8 billion years before
today the big bang happened at that time
the entire mass energy everything of the
universe was concentrated into a
singularity kind of thing a single point
and for some reason the the space time
within that expanded
in what the journalists called the big
bang yeah that's what happened 13.8
billion years ago then the milky way
formed about 13.6 billion years before
today the solar system formed 4.6
billion years before today the earth
formed 4.5 billion years before today
life emotional 3.7 7 billion years
before today
yeah the dinosaurs appeared about 240
million years before today india
collided with eurasia about
between 50 and 20 or 10 million years
before today the collision took place
for a long time it's a slow collision
but a massive collision
then
there was this impact or the the
extinction event the
impact extinction event which killed off
the non-avian dinosaurs and kept some
dinosaurs alive so that brought in the
xenozoic age the age of the mammals
right
and then if you go further ahead and
then we find that about that humanity
the best evidence we have is that
humanity emerged out of africa it our
ancestors first emerged out in the
fossil record at least in africa so the
homie needs which is the answer which is
all the great apes and their
living relatives and the extinct
relatives they arrived about on the
fossil record about 20 million years
before today right
then some more things happened then the
human chimpanzee family trees diverged
about seven or eight
million years before today most likely
seven million years before today then
you have you had all these archaic
hominin species rdp takers paranthropus
they came and went came and went then
homo habilis appeared about two and a
half million years before today then
homo erectus happened
emerged about about 1.9 million years
before today right and homo erectus was
alive until about about a hundred and
ten thousand years before today
then you had the neanderthals about
four hundred thousand years before they
need the neanderthals appeared on the
fossil record and they were alive until
recently about until 40 000 years before
today then you had the uh denisovans the
homo denis or whatever they call it then
the homo florences in indonesia that
that region and then we had homo sapiens
so homo sapiens first appears in
northern africa around three hundred
thousand years with fruity three lakh
years before today and then there was
this out of africa migration about
between ninety thousand and eighty
thousand years before today probably
around eighty five thousand years before
today and then human beings uh emerged
out of africa across the bab baba
al-mandeb strait in the from djibouti
into yemen then crossed the persian gulf
and
they reached the indian subcontinent
where they were able to sit down and
breathe a sigh of relief long journey
over there's plenty of forest and great
all the everything you need to support
life for long duration so india was the
first out of africa founders zone of the
last out of africa migration of our
ancestors homo sapiens and from india
they migrated in all directions
and that is the story in brief
of homo sapiens all right sir i hope i
have uh
i have satisfied your curiosity
okay descendant of rig vedic clans says
who are the elements
some eu experts claim that the so-called
dravidians are elamites is there any
evidence of the claim
who were these elamite people let's
let's take a look at who the elamites
were let's go and yeah let's let's put
something on the screen
so illam was
a kingdom
in iran in the south
south western iran
along the persian gulf region let's put
that on the map and see what it looks
like right
so illum i'm gonna put wikipedia on the
screen don't mind it okay please always
remember that wikipedia is not a
reliable source of
information not necessarily a reliable
source of information but i'm just
putting it here for the sake of
convenience and saving time so illum
was over here in iran let me put the map
on screen
this is what elem was right
so
what happened let's bring it back here
it is
so do you know where the persian gulf is
it's west of india yes this is the
strait of hormuz uh over here if you can
see my mouse pointer over here in this
direction you have balochistan sindh and
then gujarat and rajasthan and all that
stuff
so illam was over here
in this region east of illam was
marahashi
and east of mahashi was the sindhu
saraswati region all right so this is
this is
it was a part of persia it was a certain
kingdom in persia between i don't know
3000 bc and 500 abc thereabouts yeah
something like that
and uh so they were essentially persians
they were a branch of the persian people
and they are called the elamites and
they had their own kingdom and they had
a good relationship with the marashi
maharashi people they went to war with
the akkadians ramosh of akkad and they
apparently lost and apparently indians
fought on their behalf as allies so
there is a story indians as in the the
people of meluha the people the
saraswati
they fought
as allies with the people of marhashi
and ilam
so that is something that happened a
long long long time ago two and a half
or so thousand four and a half or so
thousand
years before today right so that is what
illam is and some people apparently
claim that the elamites the people of
illum were dravidians well what is the
evidence for that
the evidence is non-existent the
evidence is zero
i have yet to see any actual evidence
beyond people's imagination and people's
claims and people's opinions that any
such thing is true there is not
the even this so-called dravidian
race or ethnicity is is is a lie it's a
fabrication
it's a fabrication there is no such
thing as an aryan race and dravidian
race i mean
how many times times have i repeated
myself if a dravidian race exists then i
am dravidian and i'm also aryan if aryan
race exists we are all mixed if these
two races are actually a thing then all
indians are part dravidian and part
aryan
but the truth is there is no such thing
as an aryan race and dravidian race so
these are all lies these are all claims
designed to
to mislead people right they are still
pushing their ancient colonial agenda
the white man's burden please stop
listening to this nonsense
we're gonna write our own history based
on actual facts not based on feelings
and based on narratives so yeah we need
to do research we need to do research
from the ground up that's why we need
archaeologists to go out there and dig
there are thousands of unexplored
archaeological sites in in india tens of
thousands most likely
just along one dry river you have more
than 1500 unexplored archaeological
sites so we need to get going our
government needs to empower the
archaeologists and weed out the wrong
ones and empower the right ones yeah
maybe create a new asi a professional
body instead of the bureaucratic thing
that we have today yeah so it's it's
gonna take time but the truth will
emerge like we say satyam
right so it needs to happen so these
stories there is they don't have a any
basis in fact there's not a single
actual data point that points in this
direction
so so that's what it is all right so i i
hope you understand what alum was it no
longer exists it was from 3200 bc to
about 500 bc a long period of time and
uh yeah it was in persia and their
descendants i'm sure they are part of
the persian and balochi and other
populations and maybe the iraqi
population and what not right so that's
what illum was
saurabh says have you
have you gone through the disarm
decipherment of indus valley
civilization script
by yajna devam he said that the method
to decipher any script is to use all
languages and one which showed the most
will be
the language of the particular script
and he found it to be sanskrit he solved
it as a cryptogram and even proved it to
be the president predecessor of the
brahmi script what are your thoughts on
these points i think i would not be
surprised if this is correct
yeah so what is the cryptogram what is
the cryptogram you take any text let's
say in the english language
and you replace all the letters
by some other symbols
right symbols you don't know
so you're creating a code essentially
people play these games and the code
breaking and cryptogram became all thing
so when you have a script that is not
deciphered you use it as you you treat
it as a cryptogram and then you use
logic
to try and solve it you could do one
language at a time and go through cycles
through all the languages in the world
and eventually if it is a real script
you will be able to decipher it
it provided there is enough data
or you could use educated guesses to
make the process faster so in the case
of the saraswati hindu script
it's either sanskrit or tamil these are
the two old languages in india
there's always this fight going on but
which is the oldest i don't care yeah
um
so i am sure what yajna dev did was he
or she would have compared it with
sanskrit and with tamil and
um
done the process of of solving
cryptogram
however it is done yeah i'm not an
expert in that yeah but i understand the
overall
rough concept
and
to no one's great surprise surprise it
seems that it is sanskrit and i am i
have not yet studied the paper uh i
think there's a paper that he or she has
published or put out
on
put out on the internet so it is
something i am yet to see and yet to
study in detail i have been very busy in
past couple of past few weeks so i have
not yet had the opportunity to do to do
that
i will do it and i will not be surprised
at all if it is indeed sanskrit
i think this was a problem that was
waiting to be solved it was essentially
kind of a low hanging fruit i've been
saying this for a long time we need to
use
scientific methods
to solve this and and if it is if it is
deciphered
great job i think the the person
deserves at least a padma award for that
if this is indeed the case yeah so let
me let me find some time and go through
it and then i will
revisit this question
in the future but yeah i'm i'm excited
to hear about this
all right manoj says in the previous
video you mentioned that it would be in
china's interest to attack india before
attacking taiwan if that does happen
it's unlikely that india alone would be
able to stop china
also i don't see the u.s sending their
army after our stands in the russia
ukraine war nor do i think russia will
interfere
russia might want to stand with india
but going against one of their fewest
friends left china won't be in their
best interest so what do you think who
will stand with india
i think i have said this
many times nobody will stand with india
if india is engaged in a war with china
please understand this india is alone in
this matter india has no allies the u.s
is not an indian ally
russia is not an indian ally we have
shared interests we have more shared
interests with russia than we have with
the us
but we do have some shared interests
with the us because of the china
position because china is an enemy of
india and of the us as well it is hell
bent on upending the world order and
it doesn't wish india well so that's why
we have certain shared interests with
the united states
but the us is not an ally of india the
usa also in the long run does not want
to see india rise
they don't want to see another nation
come up the way china did in the past
so the u.s
both
helps india in
some ways and also hampers india and
works against india in a multitude of
ways in a multiplicity of ways so that
is the uh
kind of relationship india has with the
us when it comes to russia you are right
they are in no position to help india if
india and china go to war they would
want to help india but they are not in a
position to do it at all so if there's a
war russia will stand by and they will
remain neutral and they will call upon
both sides to stop fighting
so to make
to bring things to the conclusion
nobody
will stand with india if india
is dragged into a war by china now i
disagree with the point you're making
here that india alone won't be able to
stop china are you kidding me the
chinese won't dare push beyond a certain
point
of course our numerical superiority
isn't there their way their military
budget is like three times our military
budget
they have way more fighter planes than
india does and
and so on so forth yeah they have this
enormous numerical superiority they have
much more terrain there the higher
ground in tibet etc and yet there is
something that they are really scared of
india has the weapon that everybody is
scared of right india has nukes you
don't cross the new any nuclear power
you don't go beyond a certain line when
it comes to nuclear powers
had ukraine been a nuclear power the
russians would have never dared invade
ukraine
understand that
having this weapon gives you a certain
assurance it is mutually assured
destruction you
it's like china the chinese understand
they cross a certain red line it's
mutually assured destruction they will
be destroyed they will also be destroyed
and nobody wants that
you don't nukes are not for using in war
they are just for deterrence and india
has the deterrent and that's why the
chinese will not be able to go beyond a
certain line at most they would want to
to humiliate india in some way
militarily maybe cut off the silicon
record or maybe take our big take a big
bite out of some indian territory maybe
in the kashmir region ladakh region or
maybe in the united states
region they may want to do something
like that you know a quick short sharp
war and some big and
a rapid
uh but small but not very small
territorial gain that sort of thing that
was that is what would what they would
want to do at best
and even that is extremely risky for
them
right it's extremely risky so i
completely disagree with this contention
or respectfully that india won't be able
to stop china hell no the chinese won't
dare go go beyond a certain point so
india is
that's the good thing about india
there is i mean there are so many things
that are going wrong and things that are
not going as well as we would want them
to go but at least we have
this
we have the nukes
we have something that everyone is
scared of i mean we don't want to bully
the world and push the world around and
act as somebody who who goes around
saying
like the pakistanis do we don't do that
but
the chinese will not dare to push india
beyond a certain point yeah
okay summer says at a time when china
and thailand are holding military drills
dr s jaishankar india's foreign minister
visited thailand on the occasion of
celebration of 75 years of indo-thai
diplomatic ties
what's the objective of this visit
thailand is also a u.s ally it doesn't
want to take sides between washington
and beijing why is thailand neutral
lots of questions packed into one so i
am not aware of this visit but i'm
assuming it's it's it's the real news
okay
so uh if it's been 75 years since we had
indo thailand diplomatic ties it means
that it
the ties began after 1947.
we've had diplomatic ties and other ties
with thailand for thousands of years
okay that's a whole different story but
yeah official diplomatic relations after
india became apparently independent 47
that's what we mean
so what's the deal what is thailand's
position geopolitically uh you say that
thailand is the u.s ally they are also
doing certain things with the chinese
holding joint military drills thailand
also has good relations with india what
is going on
what's going on
why is thailand neutral why should
thailand not be neutral
why should i thailand take someone's
side what will they gain by doing so
what does thailand gain by taking sides
thailand
let's see okay we haven't done the map
here right let's map
okay where is our map
i need to bring the map onto the screen
so that we understand what's going on
come on come on where's the map here's
the map
here's a map
so for those who may not perhaps know
okay i i don't blame you for that it's
your
teachers who are to blame thailand is a
neighboring country of india you may not
realize it but it is the case see this
is the andaman sea i'm sure you know
where it is yes we have the andaman
nicobar islands and if you just cross
the andaman sea you reach phuket
it's just across the ocean it's just
across the andaman sea so thailand is
india's maritime neighbor just like
indonesia is a closed maritime neighbor
of india so india has two neighbors that
most people are not aware of
one is indonesia one is thailand right
so what is the deal with thailand what
is their geopolitical position first of
all if you see the size of the nation
it's a reasonably small sized nation yes
maybe the size of uttar pradesh
something like that
not a very large nation
and
obviously they are no match for a
massive nation like china which is
almost right next door yeah so they
would want to keep a nation like china
mollified pleased and you know act nice
play nice thailand is never going to be
well
you can't say you never said never but
in the foreseeable future you don't see
thailand emerging is a is a major
geopolitical power
so when you are a small sized nation
with a
with a modest economy and a modest
military what you do is you smile to
everybody and act nice to everybody be
respectful to everyone right especially
those who can be dangerous to you now
india is is not a threat to thailand
india is not a threat to anybody so the
thai people the nation of thailand has
no fear when it comes to india whom do
they fear they fear two nations more or
less one is china because it's the
massive
beast next door
and the other nation that the the
thailand fears is the united states
because it is the global hegemon
and so
thailand is playing nice with both
nations and it is not taking sides you
take one side the other guy will get
upset you take his side the other guy
gets upset instead of doing that just
play
the safe game stay neutral
engage with the chinese in some things
here and there and engage with the
americans on other things right that's
how it is
and
why do i say that the thai that thailand
fears the us
look at the news in the past two three
years
when was it was it 2018 2019 2020 2021
one of these years there was this
spontaneous spontaneous eruption of
protests
by well-educated students in beijing
they took the the city hostage
yeah
wearing with pink hair and green hair
and that sort of thing asking for more
democracy and freedom and all that it
happened spontaneously out of nowhere
have you not seen this before it's
called a color revolution
and then after a few months it just
disappeared overnight vanished overnight
so clearly somebody is orchestrating
things behind the scenes
it could have served as a warning to the
thai government to
fall in line or else
and there's only one nation that that is
an expert at staging these apparently
spontaneous color revolutions in mass
protests it's the us
everyone knows this in case you don't
know it please grow up
please learn this look around you look
around what's happening not only what's
up in the world
so that's why the thai
the thai government is afraid of the us
obviously it's afraid of the us thailand
is
a constitutional monarchy is it
something like that it's a military
government
their head of state is the king and they
may or may not have some form of
democracy which is just in name that's
how thailand has always been the past 60
70 80 years after the world war ii
essentially if there is democracy it's
it's a nominal democracy it's not a real
democracy and
listen it's their business what they do
with the nation who are we to pass
judgment but the americans would like to
pass judgment especially if the if there
is something to gain yeah so the
americans want to establish control
everywhere exert control everywhere so
they they have this thing about
democracy and human rights it's a stick
that beat every country with whenever it
is
expeditious for them to do so
so that's why the thai government is
afraid of the u.s they fear the u.s so
that's why they try to keep the us happy
they're also scared of china because
china is right next door and they don't
want to displease china
so that is the balancing act
thailand is playing when it comes to
india good relations form relations they
don't fear india because india doesn't
threaten anybody
so that is the situation and i hope that
explains some of it yes
they just says were there any
civilizations before the indus valley
civilization all right
the indus valley civilization um is the
old name the the colonial name we call
it the saraswati hindu civilization or
the service for the civilization so
where was it in case someone doesn't
know let me explain where this was
it was in northern western india
northwest india the region of
gujarat
northern maharashtra
western madhya pradesh rajasthan
sindh
balochistan
punjab
jamun kashmir
on north west frontier province gandhar
all the way up to northern afghanistan
this entire region was the saraswati
hindu a
phase of india civilization so please
understand it was not a separate
civilization that has disappeared
it is it was just one
phase of india's civilization which is
an unbroken thing
we don't know when indian civilization
started it started way before ten
thousand years before today
and the saraswati sindhu phase was one
phase of indian civilization
that phase
came and went but the people did not
disappear the civilization did not
disappear there was climate change the
great river dried out and the people
dispersed to other places some people
went westwards and went out of india but
most of the people went eastwards some
settled down in the ganga yamuna region
some settle down in gujarat some in
rajasthan some went northwards to punjab
and kashmir some went to gandhara that's
what happened the culture was exactly
the same there is no cultural break
right so there is continuous cultural
continuity in india going back more than
10 000 years so if you look at the
cultural artifacts that you find in the
archaeological record in the saraswati
region it's the same culture as what
people practice today the majority of
people practice today right
so that's what it is
so
it is so the saraswati hindu
civilization is one phase
of india's unbroken civilizational
continuity
and the oldest civilization that we know
of anywhere in the world is indian
civilization it is still
present it has still not been broken it
still exists it began more than ten
thousand years ago now some people will
say there is something called gobekli
back
is one
archaeological site somewhere in
anatolia
please understand the difference between
a single archaeological site and an
entire civilization
there is a difference and people
i i see this question every day but
you say india is the oldest civilization
but but go back to the pace older
please understand a single
archaeological site is not a
civilization
i i don't blame you all for this it's
your teachers who are to blame it's the
education system that is to blame that
has never taught anyone what is the
meaning of civilization a civilization
is an extended thing it's a large thing
a single village or a single
archaeological site is not a
civilization it's just a tribal outpost
even though it may be sophisticated for
example yeah people say there is a
killer d civilization there is a
civilization here by civilization there
no it's all part of the overall indian
civilization you see the same
characteristics everywhere
so go back
is just one archaeological site it does
not represent a civilization and it is
not the oldest archaeological site that
we know of the oldest archaeological
site that we know of thus far is the
submerged city in the gulf of khambath
that may be more than 12 thousand years
old and it was a fully developed city
like rakhigarhi
or kalibangan or mohenjo or
fully developed city
it is 40 meters below the the surface of
the ocean
it's about 30 kilometers from the shore
so the last time that region was
overground was at least 10 000 years
before today and it would have taken
centuries to build a city that size and
of that sophistication you know well
planned city with with roads and and
regular rectangular buildings and all
that it's not easy it takes time to
build that
so uh
that as far as we know and it's not just
one city it's it's a cluster of cities
under the ocean
yeah in the gulf of kamath so that
gives you an idea of how ancient indian
civilization is
that it's not one archaeological site
it's a it's a cluster i think it's
called the gulf of khambhat
archaeological complex or something that
it's called yeah
and our asa has done nothing this far
all we know is that it exists they
discovered this but after that they did
nothing anyhow so the old civilization
that we know of that anybody knows of
anywhere in the world is indian
civilization and to everyone's surprise
it still exists we are part of it even
though we may be deceived
and mentally colonized but we are still
carrying the flame in some way or the
other so please keep carrying it
the reformer 007 says what's the origin
of the balochi people
so my dear friends where is balochistan
in case someone doesn't know let us see
where it is you know just always good to
see
so we know where india is yes you go
west of india there is this uh
this this here
nation state which is currently here
it's called pakistan and then west of
pakistan we have this region called
balochistan
so
let's go deeper here we have the port
city of gwadar we have the port city of
chabahar chabahar is in iran guadal is
in pakistan currently all of this region
is called balochistan so about half of
it is in pakistan half of it is in iran
right
it's a large region
it's a significantly large region and
it's very rich in resources and all that
so that is balochistan
now if you go to balochistan what do the
balochi people look like they look like
indians
their language is a pure it's a properly
indian language it sounds indian you can
actually understand much of it
the closest languages
to balochi
would be
sindhi and kachi and gujarati in
rajasthan i suppose
yeah
so that is what balochistan is now what
is the origin of the balochi people the
origin of the balochi people is the same
as the origin of the indian people same
exact same there is no difference it is
not a separate ethnicity it is not a
separate ethnic group or a separate
race or whatever people call it yeah
so if you want to actually go deeper
into the origin of the balochi people
there are certain hypotheses that one
could make yeah
so uh
i think i spoke about this
last week
yeah the battle of the ten kings that
happened god knows how many thousands of
years ago it's the oldest recorded uh
battle or or conflict in human history
so it happened along the banks of the
river
the river
ravi
it was then called the purushini
so this is the river that uh that lahar
is built on top of lahore sits on top of
this river on the banks of this river so
this battle took places somewhere in
this region between uh king sudas
and an entire coalition of western vedic
clans so it was indians fighting indians
vedic people fighting vedic people in
the rig vedic or pre vedic era
so on the one hand you have just one guy
king sudas with his army with his people
on the other hand you have this entire
coalition of more than 10 different
clans they are not tribes please don't
please understand these are not tribes
these are clans extended families
so what were the clans involved in this
battle you had the pakhta klan the
parshu clan the parshwa clan the preto
clan the madrid the vishne the alina the
shimyu uh the the the the rohi the
balana clan clan the brigu clan and so
on so it is believed that the balana
clan
gave their name to the region of bolan
and bolan is in balochistan so maybe if
you want to go deeper into the the facts
then most probably
the
circumstantial evidence seems to
indicate that the ancestors of the
balochi people of the people of the
balana bolana region where the bhalana
clan which is a very ancient
vedic rigvedic
of indians of ancient indians and their
descendants could be the people of balan
balochistan
okay so that is what i can say and we
don't know for sure but it does appear
to be that way
okay amman hussain risby says you said
there are there's no substantial
evidence of sati anywhere in in history
but in my class 12 history text book it
is mentioned that francois bernier a
french traveler who visited india in the
seventh century in the 17th century
witnessed sati in front of his eyes
should that not be counted as evidence
he came to india and he witnessed
something like this it is a terrible
occurrence isn't it
terrible indians are so evil and so
primitive
so here's the thing
if you go a little bit into the history
of this
this fine gentleman mr francois bernie
you will discover
that he is the originator
of scientific racism
this entire idea of various races the
allegedly negro race the alleged
australoid race the alleged drabidian
race the alleged caucasian race these
are all completely unscientific concepts
but this fellow mr francois bernier is
the guy who introduced these horrific
racist
concepts and and he turned termed them
as science and this continued for a
couple of centuries i think in some
places it still continues lots of people
believe that race is a thing the nazis
certainly believe that and you know what
what happened as a consequence of that
it all began with mischief
so this gentleman
this fine wonderful person came to india
and he said that he witnessed indian
women being burned alive forcibly
against the vision and so on
okay so he made this claim why should we
believe this claim
tomorrow uh mr joe biden will say that i
saw ufo out of my window
should we believe the claim
why should we believe it do we have
photographic evidence of it do we have
video evidence of it do we have an
interview with an alien we have none of
these things we have someone's claim
a claim is just a claim without evidence
it means nothing
so this guy comes to india he spends
some time in india then he writes a book
and says i saw this and i saw that
why should we believe that
why should we believe it
will it hold up in a court of law let's
say you go to the court and produce this
book as evidence that this thing
happened the court will throw it out
the court will want evidence actual
evidence not a claim made by somebody
so it doesn't work like that
if some guy comes to india says i
witnessed this and i witnessed that and
i witness all kinds of things it means
nothing why should we believe it
why should we believe it they have made
all kinds of outlandish claims they used
to say these europeans that they when
they went to
to
puri in orisha
thousands of people would be crushed
under the wheels of the rata the
jagannatharat it is a lie we know it's a
lie it we
that is there is a horrific sin in
hinduism nobody would ever do that do
that but they claim that hindus
sacrifice thousands of people under the
wheels of this great wrath the
juggernaut and people still believe that
indra it is a complete lie and a
complete fabrication
they also used to claim that indians
sacrificed newborn children to the river
ganga by drowning them in the ganga that
is again obviously we all know it's a
lie but these are the claims people
europeans used to make after coming to
india so there is this well established
track record of of lying about india and
and
creating this false atrocity narrative
about india
so given this track record
why should we believe
a proven racist why
please think logically just because
something is written in your goddamn
textbook doesn't mean it's true
understand that please understand think
logically look at the data and the
evidence at hand and then
then
try to use your intelligence which you
do have the gods have given you
intelligence use it
to the right effect please
i mean if you watch this channel you
should learn a little bit of that at
least little bit that's what i'm hoping
for right
all right all right moving on
uh dikku says uh were all the
mahajanapadas in northern india and not
in southern india
um so what are the mahajanapadas the
mahajanapadas 16 great
people's republics
so
in the vedic
era of indian history and and after the
vedic era of industry we had hundreds of
kingdoms in india hundreds of kingdoms
and they were all governed in republican
fashion they were all people's republics
jana brothers
you know the chinese claim that they are
a jana pada they call themselves the
people's republic of china the janapada
of china
anyhow so we had all these people's
republics the form was a hybrid the form
of government governance was a hybrid
form of governance kings would be
elected
and they would be
um
answerable to the people and there would
be a committee of experts or committee
of
ministers or whatever who would also be
elected by the people that sort of thing
so you would have kings yeah it would be
a monarchy and the king's word would be
final but the king would still be
answerable to the people and the king if
he or did not perform well or did
something wrong the king could be
deposed and removed by the people so
that was the kind of democracy we had in
india these were the people's republics
and out of all these republics we had 16
great republics the mahajanapadas right
so that's what it was now the question
is where all these mahajanapadas in
northern india and none in south india
i can think of at least one mahajanapada
the asaka or asmakar
the mahajanapada
that was in southern india in peninsular
india in the region of andhra pradesh
um southern maharashtra karnataka that
region
the thing is this
these mahajanapadas they existed a very
long time ago
they existed before buddhism was even
born in india yeah
so
it's at least 3 000 or so years before
today so because of that and because we
have lost all the written records of our
history or most of them
in all the great on those all those
horrible fires that were lit in india's
universities and libraries so we don't
have the exact
data
to tell us where exactly these
mahajanapadas were located we know the
rough
geographical region where they would
have been so in the case of the asmaka
maha janapada it was in southern india
peninsula india let me put that on the
screen
so it would have been somewhere in in
the deccan region
southern maharashtra telangana andhra
pradesh
maybe some parts of karnataka that
region
so yes this was a mahajanapada in the
southern
portion of india now people think of
india as something that's divided north
and south and people are separate we are
separate people and all that nonsense
that is so untrue
so untrue
let me give you a couple of examples
during the satvahana period
in the in the first millennium a.d
you had on one
in the southern region of india you had
the satwanga empire and to the north
west of the south you had the
mahakshatrapaz the indus
the westerns the western
satraps now in the case of uh so one of
the great kings of the of the saath
vahanas was gotham
yes he was their greatest king
and
one of the great kings of these kytheons
of the mahaksha tribes
ii
now we know for a fact that the daughter
of rudra damon ii
married
the son of gautama putra satakarani
and she was the queen of the of these uh
satwanas
yeah
so you have north indians or west
indians skythians marrying into a
southern dynasty and their daughter
becomes the queen of the dynasty and she
produces offspring who rule the dynasty
right so you see this inter-marriage we
also had the example of prabhavati gupta
the son of chandragupta ii i think
one of the greatest emperors of india of
all time the great emperor of the gupta
dynasty his daughter prabhavati gupta
she married
a king of the wakatak empire in southern
india
and her husband died after just five
years
so for
more than two decades she ruled as the
king queen of the vocatics
and then her children
she had two or three sons and at least
two of her sons were kings
after her
so you have this inter marriage that was
happening for thousands of years there
is no such thing as north indian people
and south indian people everybody is
mixed this has been happening for
thousands of years in india but your
teachers and your textbooks don't teach
you these things so we all think of
india as this is divided into
compartments
there is no such thing as a north
ethnicity and a south indian ethnicity
everybody is the same that's why we all
have the same genetics please understand
that
okay other says please tell me about the
konkani language which looks similar to
sanskrit while listening to words and
with her with some minor differences
it's one of the languages that's less
known to indians
so where is konkan let's go back to the
map
where is konkan
so konkan is the west coast of india
that region southern maharashtra
essentially yeah
um
the
malevolent etc goa also one could say is
part of konkani
so western maharashtra the coastal
region
south west in maharashtra essentially is
konkan if i am not mistaken if i'm wrong
please don't hold it against me but that
rough region overall is konkan
now the konkani language is classified
as
a so-called indo-aryan language i think
it is in some ways
reasonably similar
and reasonably close to the marathi
language yes
so uh the question is
please tell me about this language well
it's an ancient language that
that obviously uh
is a descendant
of sanskrit
now
here's an interesting tidbit interesting
piece of information
uh i spoke about the vacation empire
right the vacations had a king whose
name was pravara sena ii
he was the son
of prabhavati gupta
the
gupta
the the queen of the great gupta emperor
chandragupta ii i think right uh so his
mother was a gupta princess but he was a
king of the vacations
ii
he lived in the 5th century
now this guy
he was a king but he was also a poem and
he wrote a poem called the sithu bandha
which is about lord rama conquering
lanka that sort of thing and you do you
know which language he wrote this poem
in he did not write it in sanskrit he
wrote this poem
in a language called maharashtri prakrit
and as far as i personally personally
know it's the oldest
known evidence of this language the
maharashtri prakrit and it is
maharashtri prakrit that was the
ancestor of both marathi and konkani
5th century ad
all right so i hope you have learned
something new from this
and some people believe that the
prakrit is just one language and it came
before sanskrit i think some youtube
channels are trying to uh promote this
narrative please understand something
prakrit is not one language it's a whole
bunch of languages it's a whole bunch of
upper branch languages you had a prakrit
in maga you had a practice in in south
of india you had practice in the west of
india various prakrits in various parts
of india which were all upper branch
languages descendant languages of of
classical panini and sanskrit pali
itself was a prakrit it was a descendant
of sanskrit it was an upper branch a
kind of distorted version of sanskrit
you know you don't say dharma it's a
dhamma
it was a vernacular language it was a
low language not a classical high
language so the prakrits are a whole
family of languages a whole bunch of
languages all across india and they are
all
languages that descended from sanskrit
and one of the examples is maharashtri
prakrit that was spoken in the 5th
century a.d and a poem
in that language was written by the
great king not the great king but the
moderately great king prabhupara ii
okay king of the vac attacks
okay i hope i i threw some a little bit
of new light on this matter
okay mother says i am from sindh can you
tell me about the origin of the sunday
language in which script was it written
written before
and after the arab invasion of 712 a.d
and why did the brits change its script
into arabic at the 1850s did it have
something to do with partition um
the sindhi language
so sindh obviously in case someone
doesn't know we know where cindy is but
let's anyway put it on the screen sindh
is west of gujarat rajasthan right
the city of karachi which was once known
as
the major city in another city that is
quite large is hyderabad
yes
so sindh is to the west of gujarat and
to the west of rajasthan and to the east
of balochistan that is where sin is now
if you look at the sindhi language the
closest language to sindhi is kachi
kachi that is spoken in the khacha
region of gujarat right run of kachor
that area so the kachi language is is
very similar to sanskrit uh to say sorry
one could even consider kachi to be a
dialect of sindhi
and the other language that is closest
to sindhi
would most likely be gujarati or balochi
most likely gujarati more than balochi
so that would tell you that the that
sindhi and gujarati have if you go back
a few centuries they would have probably
a common origin
um sindh gujarat are anyway neighboring
regions of india
so
i would say cindy must have originated
from some ancient prakrit language that
came after panini and sanskrit
uh we know what languages were spoken in
in the western region of india the
western region of india saurashtra
gujarat and sindh were ruled for several
centuries close to half close to half a
millennium
by the mah chatrapas who ruled this
region yeah
um
they would have spoken some ancient form
of of prakrit the precursor of the
gujarati rajasthan languages so we don't
know quite sure which language it was
because our historians have done
nothing
to uh throw light upon this matter
but the the sindhi language comes when
did it first originate
maybe in the past somewhere in the past
1000 years yeah
so when it when it comes to the arab
invasion of muhammad bin qasim around 71
to 80 it would not be sindhi that was
there was poker in the region it would
have been
an ancestral language of sindhi maybe
old sindhi or some prakrit
prakrit language from this region yeah
that's what would have been spoken in
the region and there could be a whole
bunch of scripts that could be used for
it
before the arabic script was used for
sanskrit for for cindy i believe it was
a variant of the guru mukhi script that
was used to write sindhi if i am not
mistaken
i'm not an expert in sindhi so i may be
wrong but this is this is the gut
feeling that i have but it was most
likely a variant of the gurmukhi script
the punjabi script that was used for
sindhi and before that there were so
many different scripts in western india
northern india we had the sharda lip the
script in in north india in in in the
kashmir region and we had various other
forms of devanagari and closely related
scripts that were used in the region the
gujarati script is itself you could see
a variant of devanagari and a descendant
of the brahmi script
so um
not 100 sure but something of this sort
would have been there one of these
scripts a brahmi derived script for sure
and something that would be
closely related to either gurmukhi or
gujarati or gujarati or maybe
maybe something similar to sharda lip or
something like that that's what i can
say but uh
in all my time i have never come across
the this specific answer to this
question maybe i will do some
digging and find out if i can find
something if i do i will let you know
right
vasu allure says um i was recently
watching a cricket related documentary
series on whatever thing uh following
the australian cricket team which had
this episode of the players visiting
galipoli memorial and talking about the
anzac spirit
since a lot of indian soldiers were part
of the world wars is there a similar
kind of place where our fallen soldiers
have been buried or any kind of memorial
created from the for them outside of
india and possibly in india um
anzac all that what is that let's go
let's go to the map
so where is gallipoli gallipoli is
in the turkish straits
so in i think it was in 1915 that
winston churchill decided to
invade
turkey send a big
invasion force a maritime invasion force
and
he wanted to essentially take istanbul
so to take a stun bowl you have to go
through this straight here
the dardanelles straight
yeah you have to uh come from the aegean
sea
which is very
which is like a narrow place and then
you have to go through this very narrow
straight the dardanelles
you go into the sea of marmara and
that's where you reach istanbul and even
istanbul is the second straight here
yeah the bus for us straight
and that's what you have to cross in
order to reach the black sea
so that's why turkey occupies this very
strategic position in the world
so the british wanted to take istanbul
to do that they had to go through the
dardanelles straight
and you have chanakale here
and gallipoli somewhere nearby and
that's where all the fighting happened
yeah and the british were were pinned
down by the turks the dogs fought
brilliantly extremely bravely
and all because of the leadership of one
man mustafa kemal who was later known as
mustafa kamal atathor the father of
modern day turkey
and on the british side
on the allied side you had the
australians and the new zealanders the
anzacs and you had a whole lot of indian
soldiers who are not remembered
lots of indians fought on these beaches
and died on these beaches and there is
no memorial to them i am sure there is a
memorial for the anzac soldiers the
australian and new zealand soldiers who
fought and died here but lots of indians
died here
and as far as i know
i've not been here i've never been to
turkey but as far as i know
there is no memorial to the indians
there is an anzac thing over there or
whatever and anzac day is commemorated
every year in australia in new zealand
maybe in canada also because some
candidates were there in this entire
matter
but uh
yeah that's how it is i as far as i know
there is no memorial to the indian
soldiers who fought there and who died
there right there is no memorial in
india also for this particular event
and the thing is this
these
our men who fought and died there they
were fighting for empire
they were fighting somebody else's war
they were not fighting for india which
is the sad thing
they fought and died in vain they
fought and died to serve an oppressive
racist colonial master they got nothing
out of it their nation got nothing out
of it it was a pointless
war a pointless death pointless deaths
for indians
yeah so that's what i can say as far as
i know there is no memorial that has
been created by the indian government or
any other government
for this matter for indians who died
in gallipoli in the gallipoli campaign
okay mahesh says
it means it said that ashok changed
after the kalinga war and decided not to
fight any war after that
so why didn't any of his enemies at the
time take advantage of that and attack
the maury empire or why isn't any
record of any revolt against akbar um
i apologize against uh ashok
apologies
one must not make such comparisons
anyhow so what is the deal
so ashok changed after the kalinga right
let's let's put ashok on the screen
ashoka empire let's see what that looks
like am i able to find something
more empire
let me put that on the screen right i'm
gonna again put a wikipedia thing on the
screen please remember it's not entirely
trustworthy i know what i'm doing so i
can do that you don't do it
so this is the mori empire
at its height
right
so this is what the mauryan empire
looked like when it was at its peak and
it was at its peak at its greatest
extent under emperor ashok the great
this is what it looked like
and before the kalinga war happened
there would be a
a hole here where
where ashok did not have control
and he wanted
to establish control over the entirety
of peninsular india and even if you go
south
the tamrapani tamraparani empire the
tamraparani kingdom and the various
southern indian kingdoms were vasal
states of ashoka
which means that they were all under his
control even sri lanka was under his
control
yeah nominally or effectively or
whatever
so essentially ashok
had established after the kalinga war
complete authority and complete control
over the entirety of jambo dweeb the
entire subcontinent indian subcontinent
so when you see that and when you see
this map do you see any enemies left for
him to fight
do you see anybody who was capable of
offering any kind of resistance to ashok
once he had dealt with kalinga in the
way he did
no
the map tells you the entire story you
need to know
aft by defeating kalinga and and
absorbing it into his empire that was it
he had no enemies left
he had established complete supremacy
over jambudvipa or the indian
subcontinent
and that is why after the kalinga
conquest he said that i am now a
peaceful man
i now believe in dharma dhamma
damn sarnam kachami
yeah and now i will not fight anymore
there was no more war left to fight
unless he wanted to go west of
afghanistan or whatever right
so that's what it is
he had crushed all his enemies
there was nobody left to oppose him not
a single person
his
control and authority over the indian
subcontinent was absolute
so that's why he became peaceful now i
can afford to be peaceful i don't have
any enemies left so now let's do peace
okay so that's what happened there was
nothing left to nobody left to oppose
him he had crushed every single enemy
that he had
so that's why
there is no record of any such thing
because no such thing happened
okay reyes says japan is doing a
nationwide urge to drink alcohol
campaign especially for youngsters sake
viva
for money they mentioned to be less
reliable in the us to increase their
defense budget japan has 6.11 trillion
gdp dollars yeah
their civilians died more in suicides
than kobe 19.
is this a selfish move or a necessary
action is this a move by japan to free
themselves as a vasal state of the us
even at the cost of the youth
you know
having a drinking campaign and let's say
see what's happening is that in the past
few years the the i think the revenues
of the alcohol industry the wide
industry liquor industry have dropped a
lot especially after the lockdowns you
know people were not drinking and the
japanese government had been doing these
campaigns urging
youngsters the youth to drink less
so because of that the liquor industry
the alcohol industry obviously suffered
yeah it's not doing well it's that
industry has entered the recession it's
not doing well so now for some reason
the government is saying drink more
so they are contradicting the previous
stance
and obviously there's going to be um
people are not going to be pleased with
that i'm sure there is a significant
amount of bash backlash on social media
and various other platforms against the
government that what are you doing
you've been saying all this time not to
drink less and now you're urging people
to drink more doesn't you you're doing
you turn u-turn
and even if let's say the alcohol
revenue is double
how is it going to free japan from from
their their status as the vasal said of
the u.s the japan is a vasa state of the
us because the u.s has more than 130
more than one 3-0 permanent military
bases on japanese soil that's why it's
about salt state it has nothing to do
with money
japan has a very high
gdp like you just mentioned six point
something trillion
it's nothing to do with money so i don't
know what is the end point of this
entire
campaign of urging
youngsters to drink more i think it's a
stupid thing to do
if they're doing a u-turn they're
telling
youngsters to do something that's not
good for them yeah
what japan needs
is increased birth rates and drinking
more is not gonna make
people produce more children right
so yeah i i don't get it i think it's a
silly move it reminds me of what the
chinese
do from time to time
the chinese government the chinese
communist party has millions of members
you know and millions of employees at
various levels in in the nation
district level state level province
level city level and so on these
employees are all members of the chinese
communist party and they have to follow
and obey the dictats of the uh party
bosses
so from time to time the chinese
communist party
orders its employees
to smoke more
smoke cigarettes you know
and that will apparently help the
economy and and boost the tobacco
industry and all that
i think the chinese people on average
smoke a lot anyway they have a very high
rate of smoking
and those who smoke are apparently chain
smokers so the chinese government had
ordered its government employees in a
certain state i don't remember which
state it was chandong or whatever to
smoke like two packs a day or something
like that in order to boost the the
tobacco industry's uh i don't know
performance whatever so
this
campaign by the japanese government kind
of reminds me of that it's silly and i i
i don't know what's the point it's not
going to change anything
it's not
overall going to change the fortunes of
japan you want to boost your economy you
have to take some real measures not
urging people to drink more so i think
it's a really silly thing one of the
silliest things i've heard in a long
time
all right
adithy says netaji's daughter strongly
believes her father's relics are in a
temple in japan and she's ready for a
dna test
however
as of now we understand there are no dna
presence in ashes unlike burial so what
is the dna test she's asking for and why
do the family members of netaji fail to
see dithaji in gumnami baba
yeah i have no idea see the thing is
this
lethargy subhashin raboos was a national
leader he belonged to the entire nation
he was not a private individual he was a
public personality he was the most
public of people
he was a national leader which means he
belonged to the nation
he did not belong only to his family
and
truth be told
the nation has a greater claim on him
than
some some daughter of his who is not
even an indian citizen
right so i don't care what his daughter
believes or claims that she believes it
is immaterial
nitaji is a national treasure
and the nation needs to
uh decide
make the judgment of what really
happened and
from everything we we know
uh anujdar and chandra ghosh have done
extensive research they've put out so
much
data so many facts i think it's very
clear that mithaji did not die in this
alleged plane crash which never happened
most likely most likely i am almost
hundred percent convinced that gumnavi
was nitaji and he lived until 1985. so
if his daughter makes this claim it it
makes no difference to me
she's not an indian citizen yeah she she
she doesn't have skin in the game
yeah so
if she's making some clean claims there
are many family members in the extended
bose family who have all kinds of these
political affiliations and who
i don't know they make various kinds of
claims
we don't have to take it seriously
they have a lesser claim on nitaj
bachendrabose than the nation all right
so that's just how it is uh um and about
dna test once a body is burned
dna is destroyed
heat destroys dna
now i remember another was saying that
uh maybe you can extract mitochondrial
dna from the burned charred bones
possibly you can take a chance or you
can you can try it out i'm not sure
about even if that is possible or not
um but yeah so um
even if you do a dna test it's most
likely not going to throw up anything
and the actual evidence is out there so
i don't know there's some kind of
i i don't want to make any any such
statement but it looks like
uh there is an attempt to mislead the
people
with all this yeah so i don't care of
what x person is saying or why family
member is saying
we have the evidence we have all the
information we have all the data
these researchers have done all the
research they put out all the facts in
the public public like public domain and
we can
base our judgment we can
we can judge what really happened
based on the evidence that we have not
on the opinion or the claim made by some
family member so it it
to me it's immaterial what she claims or
says that she believes it doesn't matter
right
next
okay devashes says who are the natives
of australia and how did the europeans
steal their lands similar to the case of
new zealand
the natives of australia are the
uh
indigenous australians the the so-called
australian aborigines yeah
these people so where is australia in
case i'm sure people know where
australia is because people watch
cricket but anyway
let's put that on the uh
on the screen
let's put the map on the screen where is
australia
here it is
so this
continent size island
which is in the
intersection of the indian and pacific
oceans is australia
so this
territory this continent was first
settled by ancient humans approximately
65 000 years before today
and those humans were the ancestors of
today's native australians indigenous
australians or so-called australian
aboriginal people
these people are dark-skinned they have
lived there for more than 60 000 years
and about five thousand years before
today
there was a migration into this region
into australia from india we know this
for a fact because today
the australian native people
approximately 10 percent of their genome
of their genetics
has indian origin it is of indian origin
and this event this change in the
genetics happened about 5000 years
before today
so you could say that the australian
aboriginal people are to some extent our
relatives if we if you are indians right
now what happened is that
around
less than 250 years ago
the first european settlement
began in australia less than two and a
half centuries before today
and today as you can see the australians
have been the native australians have
been marginalized
they are treated like
not second class but third class
citizens yeah
they are relegated to the interiors of
the of the of the continent where it's
where the conditions are dry and harsh
and the europeans and the european
origin people they live on the coastline
all the nice climatic regions adelaide
adelaide melbourne sydney brisbane
tasmania there are no natives left in
tasmania they have all been eradicated
hunted down like wild animals
so that's what it is australia is stolen
territory they conducted systematic
genocide over there they treated the
australian aboriginal people like flora
and fauna like animals not like human
beings
and
they would
kidnap the children
and take them over to boarding schools
and and force them to marry white people
and to in order to change the ethnicity
of the of these kids and all that just
terrible terrible business horribly
atrocious very racist that's that's the
legacy that australia has today they
pretend to be very nice and all that but
this is the legacy that they are
laboring under and even today the native
australians have not been given justice
yeah
that's what it is so that in brief is
the story you can look it up in more
detail
okay rohan says we talk about
decolonization of our society what about
decolonization of our minds our society
still worships people who are high in
status
how do you think decolonization of our
society and our minds will happen and we
are talking about the colonizer's
language yes very observant sir yeah
so the main problem we are pointing out
is that our society worships people who
are high in status
um
have you noticed
that no matter what society you go to
they all
hold high status people in high esteem
in high regard
whether it's in the us whether it's in
europe whether it's in africa whether
it's in china whether it's in japan
whether it's india whether it's russia
everybody
holds
high status people
in high regard
that's not a problem
the problem is when you assign the wrong
people high status
in the past
before
india's colonization at the hands of
barbarians before the past millennium of
humiliation a certain kind of people
would be given high status people who
were either
highly knowledgeable scholars yeah
indians even today indians are they
worship knowledge even today
indians hold people who are
knowledgeable to be in
in very high regard
but today indians are so confused they
also hold entertainers in high regard
and give entertainers very high status
so the question is not that the problem
is not that we worship people who are
high in status the problem is that we
give the wrong people high status
that is the problem
we give entertainers celebrity status
and that is something we have copied
from the west we are aping
the west like monkeys ape humans that's
what we're doing
in india we worship entertainers
i have nothing against entertainers it's
it's it's a it's a good business option
i mean it's a good career choice if you
have the quality and to and if you have
the ability to entertain people but
entertainers
should we give them the kind of high
status they have today
that's the thing
the people who contribute the most to
society they should be given high status
not people who entertain society and
who act for money
yeah so that is the problem the problem
is wrong values we are putting we are
giving the wrong people high status not
just entertainers there are other
examples as well let's not go into all
the examples and make a list of that but
you get the point
there is nothing wrong with worshiping
like you say high status people the
problem is when you give the wrong kind
of people high status and you don't give
high status to the people who actually
deserve it that is the problem that is
very the indian society is going wrong
and that's what the west is also going
wrong and india is aping the west and
that is the entire problem
decolorization and of the society in
mind will
we are not even beginning that process
right now yeah
everything is colonized our
government system our governance system
is called colonize our bureaucracy is
colonized
the laws are colored in laws the
constitution is a colonial constitution
the language like you like you very
aptly and observantly point out is which
we are using is a colonial language if
you don't speak good english you will
not get a good job if you don't speak
good english you cannot go and fight a
court case
you see that's where we are colonized
so
that process has to start at the top
yeah
but that will be done when the political
climate is right i suppose i don't know
yeah
so that's where we are
okay saurabh says what was the history
of witch burning
is this widespread or rare in european
society did their great personalities do
this or even in support of this in the
past
i ask this because they bash
indians for the alleged sati practice
by fabricating the issue okay what is
the history of which burning
so to understand the history of witch
burning we have to first understand the
concept of a witch what is a witch of
which what are the characteristics of a
perch and person who is a witch
the first characteristic of a person who
is a witch is that it's a female
some men were also alleged to be witches
but that was a very small percentage
overwhelming the overwhelming majority
of people who were alleged to be witches
were women
okay
now where did witch hunting happen in
europe in west in western society also
in north america the salem witch trials
and all that and when did this start
happening
after the conversion of europe to
christianity
correct me if i'm wrong
so
the people who are targeted for being
witches were mostly overwhelmingly women
this only happened in western society in
europe and in north america and maybe
other places possibly but wherever your
best western culture and thirdly this
happened this started happening after
the christianization of europe
so now let's understand what they define
as a witch they define a person as a
witch
what kind of person do they call a witch
someone
who apparently
uh worships the devil in some way or the
other now what do we mean by devil
worship does it mean that they have a
statue of the devil and they're praying
to the statue no no no no
anything can be construed as
devil worship if you don't follow the
exact orders of your priest you are a
devil worshipper
if you have some
ancient knowledge
that
they don't want you to have then you're
a devil worshiper see
in ancient society especially in europe
in the celtic
parts of europe in the slavic parts of
europe and traditionally all across the
indo-european world
women were healers
in india
before we had hospitals and all that it
was elderly ladies who would assist in
childbirth
they would have the special skills and
knowledge to do it properly
and similarly in europe also it was
elderly ladies
who had this medicinal knowledge of
herbs ayurvedic knowledge and childbirth
midwifery and various other things you
know healing and all that
now
this was all part of the ancient
indo-european culture which manifested
it itself in different ways all across
europe
now once the christianization started
the church wanted to stamp out every
single manifestation of the old culture
and this healing
skills and this knowledge of healing was
part of the old culture
and it is something that gave women high
status in society
and
they did not want women to have high
status women were supposed to be
inferior to men
therefore
any woman who had any such ancient
knowledge
would be deemed to be a witch
and they would burn them alive
because of this reign of terror
this entire thing went out of i mean
the the position that women had in
society
evaporated women became sub-subordinate
to men
and women became became
for centuries highly oppressed all the
old knowledge was wiped out the the
knowledge of healing the knowledge of of
horrible medicine of the ayurvedic
medicine that was there all that and
that's what we call the dark ages of
europe horrible horrible time
all kinds of diseases all kinds of
superstitions
apparently
which which
i mean superstitions were supposed to be
driven out by the church but the reverse
of that happened
yeah these are all facts it's been very
well documented okay uh you know what
was the most
popular book for the longest time in
europe
the most popular or maybe the second
most popular book in europe for the
longest time for more than a century it
was the malayus maleficarum
the hammer of the witches it was a
manual on how to identify witches and
how to torture them to death
lovely
so yeah that is which burning
and because they have been so
misogynistic and
horrific that's why they try to
attribute those characteristics to other
people and that's why they invented this
fake tradition of sati
there we are
okay vishal says why did the ottoman
turk sultan muhammad the conqueror
believed that his empire was a
continuation of the roman empire rather
than its replacement was it a publicity
understand he did not believe any such
thing
he made the claim to legitimize his rule
over the people of this region okay
let's see where turkey is just just in
case since in case somebody doesn't know
so muhammad the conqueror
laid siege on
on
constantinople
and that siege lasted months and months
and months it was brutal it was barbaric
eventually he was able to break through
yeah
constantine
and
yeah he he eventually won and he was
able to conquer constantinople and
become
and establish uh his
authority over the region and that was
the beginning of the ottoman empire
muhammad the conqueror that was the
beginning of the ottoman empire with the
the the red apple constantinople as its
capital they called it constantini
now
this region
was the old byzantine empire the city of
constantinople was originally called
byzantine or byzantium right
it was renamed to constantinople by the
emperor constantine the guy who
officially made christianity the state
religion of the roman empire so the
byzantine empire was the eastern roman
empire it was a contingent of the
western roman empire like i said the
capital city moved from rome to
constantinople at some point in time in
the first millennium a.d
so
this region
trace and anatolia was the eastern roman
empire now this fellow muhammad the
conqueror conquered the region
and he was a pretty brutal guy like all
turks at the time were right
so to legitimize his rule and legitimize
his authority over the people of this
region he declared himself to be
the next kaiser room the next caesar of
rome
yeah so he said that i am going to honor
the old traditions i am going to honor
the old roman empire by saying that it
my rule is a continuation of that i am
the next roman empire emperor
so that's what it did it was simply to
legitimize his rule
over his newly conquered subjects he did
not believe in any such thing he knew
what he was he knew he was a turk but
yeah just to legitimize his rule he made
this claim that's all it is nothing more
than that
okay lagera online says
yeah hello hi uh your views on one of
the most controversial cult guru or show
rajneesh
look i don't know much about osho
rajanesh what i can tell you is that
when i was a little kid
in the 1980s i had seen some documentary
about him there was there was a french
documentary about rajneesh there was
this bunch of french travelers who were
traveling across the world in the grand
raid or whatever and they were traveling
across the us and they came across
across this place called rajneesh puram
in the us and then they met the people
of this place and they they
took they they interviewed some of them
and they probably possibly interviewed
rajneesh as well
so i remember seeing this as a little
kid and i was like fascinated who is
this guy this indian guy who has all
this big bunch of of american followers
and they're all worshiping him and he's
wearing this weird clothes looks like
some kind of mongol conqueror or
something i don't know what it was you
know sitting on a throne and all that i
found it really
strange but fascinating as a kid
and later on we know that he died and
the his life and
his persona itself is controversial some
people said that he was well
you know a bad influence on people some
other people said that he had the spark
of divinity in him and he was an
absolute genius
i haven't really studied his life in
detail or anything
i've listened to a few of his you know
snippets of his speeches i think
it's fascinating what he says you know
it makes a lot of sense he clearly was
an extraordinarily sharp intellect very
intelligent person for sure
um
he obviously had this ashram in pune the
rajini ashram where people said all
kinds of well
certain activities took place uh i i
don't know much about that
and
yeah there were these there were some
controversies there were some some
criminal cases against them in the u.s
some people say that rajonesh himself
was involved in that some people say
that somebody else misled him and
hijacked the organization and the things
some people blame sila
what's her name sheila right
a lady called sheila who was his right
hand
person
some p and perhaps she claims that she
was trying to warn him and you know take
him in the right direction i don't know
it's a mess
yeah so i think he's a fascinating
character
i from whatever i've i've heard of him
he sounds like an extremely intelligent
person
and we don't know what the real at least
i don't know what the truth is but i
think is a very interesting person and
whatever whatever i've heard of him
speaking it's it's very interesting and
it makes a lot of sense but i don't know
a whole lot about him so that is as much
as i can say interesting character but i
don't know everything about him
jade joy says who was notre damos and
does any of his prophecies really come
true if yes what prophecies he made
about india listen i don't know much
about this guy his name was michel the
nostradam he was french he lived
somewhere in the
i don't know last 500 or so years and he
was apparently a fortune teller he could
see the future you know he had some
certain things certain ways of doing it
he would enter a trance state and then i
don't know
i don't know he would receive visions or
something and then he would write it
down in these french quatrains you know
worse
rhyming verse and all that and that's
what we still have with us and
apparently he made predictions about the
future now i remember something
um
i had this i
i used to buy this second hand books you
know from time to time and one of the
books i had bought was an old book from
the 1970s about the predictions of
nostradamus
and this is after
9 11.
you know the september 11 bombing of the
twin towers in new york
this book i bought it after this event
happened but the book was printed in the
1970s it was an old secondhand book and
in the book
the prediction was there that there
would be an attack
on new york city from the sky
fire will come from the sky and the date
was pretty close to the actual date 2001
yeah and it mentioned new york city so
that was like uncanny yeah that book was
printed a couple of decades two three
decades before this actually happened so
yeah that is something i found really
interesting but yeah so yeah i think
it's interesting but i don't know much
about
him beyond that
some people say that he has made
predictions about india that the next
great uh what india will be the next
great superpower and some world
conqueror will
something like that i've heard i'm not
quite sure about that but yeah there was
a time when i was quite interested in
these things i found it fascinating
um but i haven't really kept up with
this matter so yeah it's it's
interesting it's certainly interesting
to
that such people existed and they
apparently made predictions that
seem to have to some extent come true it
seems he even predicted napoleon
and histor you know that's also
interesting so i'm not sure how true it
is that he actually came up with this
prediction or did somebody fabricate it
later on we're not sure but yeah it's
interesting
that's what i can say
okay bharat says this may sound like a
stupid question no sir no question is
stupid go ahead ask me as a student i
would like to know how can one retain
the historical data in their minds tell
us with your experience how to remember
things like dates and names and details
thank you
i am not good at remembering dates i
often get my dates wrong
yeah i don't memorize dates i will tell
you which century something happened in
yeah i don't remember the exact date
when this guy lived um
nostradamus i can't remember right now i
love to google it
so i don't memorize dates i typically
know roughly when it happened
um
so that's one thing i get things wrong
from time to time i speak
like this without doing any preparation
you will find lots of videos in which
i've made mistakes here and there i
don't care about that yeah
i one example i
tend to mix up gory and guznavi
i tend to mix these two guys up all the
time
i i
have tried to look it up the exact dates
who comes first who comes who comes next
but
still i tend to mix these two guys up
yeah because i'm not really interested
in these guys i don't i don't find these
two guys interested in korean kaznavi
so the thing is this
i never memorize days you try to
memorize dates it's gonna become a
problem
and i only remember things that i find
interesting gauri ghaznavi not
interesting i still can't remember who
came first who came later but i can
always look it up and refer to it so
form i can only speak for myself i don't
memorize things i don't memorize dates
there are lots of things i forget
immediately i only remember things i
find interesting
i meet lots of people
and i forget them i am i have a very bad
memory for faces and for names
so in case i meet some of you in the
future and i met you before please
forgive me if i don't remember you i
have i have a very bad memory for faces
and names unless you are a fascinating
person
so in advance i beg your forgiveness i
am very bad at that
i
see
everybody is different this is the way i
am i remember i remember things easily
that i find interesting so that's how it
works for me
um
and yeah so that's what i can tell you
honestly truthfully
transparently that's how it works for me
i don't have this prodigious memory for
memorizing numbers and names and all
kinds of
data
i remember patterns
so when something fits into a pattern i
find it interesting and that's how i can
recollect that that's why it looks like
i know so many things i i i tend to see
patterns that's how my mind works
okay calcite says
is ashwathama from mahabharata i'm still
alive
we don't talk about these things in
public
okay mango elijah says what do you who
do you think should be the next james
bond from what i read they were looking
for someone in the early 30s so tom
hardy's out of the picture unfortunately
why don't they make veer das the next
james bond
make veer das the next james bond or
make what's his name akshay kumar the
next james bond
or amir khan
i mean diversity right why why do we
need a white person
get somebody from somewhere else and
call him this one but most likely i
think they will make uh
most likely the next james bond will be
a transgender
black mixed-raced lesbian woman of color
or something like that with pink hair or
green or something that most likely
they're going to come up with something
like that so i don't know
i would like to see somebody continue
continue the tradition i'm a man of
tradition i like tradition especially
when traditions are good yeah james bond
is a is a character that represents the
the desire of the uk to remain relevant
in geopolitics and so on but it's an
entertaining character it's something i
grew up with and something i'm kind of
attached to so i would like to see a
good
next james bond we know that daniel
craig craig is done with the role
somebody else will come will come in
um
i don't know let's see maybe
henry cavill i kind of
used to like him i'm not sure what he's
up to these days so yeah i don't know
who should be the next james one
hopefully somebody who continues the
tradition but you never know these days
everything is up for grabs they are
killing off all the heroes and
destroying all their legacies so
who knows maybe james bond is next they
already killed him off on screen right
and now they will come up with some new
story to bring up bring a new new james
bond into the picture or maybe they will
say that james bond is dead and a nude
007 is coming up who knows who knows
anything is possible
okay
i guess we are done for the the
questions i had selected now let's take
some live chat questions for a few
minutes if you have some questions
will be the next james bond well if you
are right then you're right
yeah i've heard that they were
considering idris elba
but i'm sure he's not in his 30s right
he must be in his 40s by now
the guy he's a good actor he's a he's a
an impressive actor he's of course
of african origin so not quite the
tradition of james bond but well it may
happen and i have nothing against him
he's a i think he's a good actor
but if it is supposed to be somebody in
his 30s then maybe he will not quite
fit the bill but who knows
all right all right all right what else
do we have okay rinku tiwari says please
consider my question
you want me to answer a question you
have to put the question here
see i saw your question but there's no
question please don't do such things
please please please
um
tom hiddleston who is tom middleton
or the tall guy the tall guy who played
loki
okay let's see let's see if it is him
uh
how to be successful in our goals
first of all you have to be focused it
has to be at the forefront of your mind
you can't put it on the back burner for
five days and then again think of it for
the later on
if you have a goal that you really want
to be successful right you you have to
think about it constantly and then you
have to take action
you have to take action every day that
takes you a little bit further
towards that goal right so i mean
that's what i can say that's how you do
it it's actually quite simple but simple
things are the hard death actually
so that's how it goes
all right um
what else do we have
yeah p okay the same question every day
come on
uh
okay
um
can you please tell me which is the
largest empire in indian history because
every day i see a new empire in a
different shape of every empire every
empire listen you take any empire
decade upon decade their shape of the of
the boundaries will change that's how it
just goes but the largest empire
one is the mauryan empire enormous
the entirety of jumbo dweeb yes the
entirety of the indian subcontinent
secondly the gupta empire was also kind
of comparable
it also
encompassed bahalik etc kaneshka's
empire was incredibly massive it touched
the caspian sea and the rlc it also
included the tarim beijing region the
whole of afghanistan punjab kashmir
sindh balochistan gujarat saurashtra all
the way to partly putra
and parts of dikkan as well yeah massive
massive massive
kingdom so these are some of the
kingdoms i can tell you about it is also
believe that that uh
also had an enormous empire in
uh which encompassed parts of
significant parts of central asia yeah
so these are some of the empires i can
think of off the top of my head
right
where else are we what else do we have
my thoughts on the next dalai lama well
it is for the current of for the for the
current dalai lama to decide what he
wants to do
because the next dilemma is going to be
well according to the
tibetan tradition
the next dalai lama is the reincarnation
of the current dalai lama so once the
current
lama whoever it is
passes on
dies
then they start searching for a small
child a male child who will have certain
characteristics which indicate that this
child is the reincarnation of the
previous dalai lama so that's what it's
believed
so i think the next next dalai lama
it's up to the present day dalai lama to
decide who will be the next dilemma
does he plan to reincarnate in tibet in
chinese occupied territory or does he
plan to reincarnate somewhere else
that's the first thing he has to answer
yeah and secondly does he plan to
reincarnate
or not
maybe he doesn't want to reincarnate
maybe he wants to attain nirvana and
never
and break free of the of the cycle of
rebirth
so if you are the lama i'm sure you have
the option to do that or not
so it's up to him to to make his
position clear
whether he wants to reincarnate or not
so in case he doesn't want to
reincarnate then they can make the
tradition the the
the office of the dalai lama uh
an elected office or something so it's
it's for the tibetan people and for for
dalai lama to decide about this but it
is something that is important
from multiple perspectives including a
geopolitical perspective
so yeah that's something that needs to
be taken up sooner rather than later
history of adidas in russia and baseball
in japan
how about the history of fanta in india
listen i don't know
i don't know everything in the world i i
am stumped i have no answer here
baseball in japan i could i could give
you a reasonably uh
uh an educated guess
i would say that baseball would have
been introduced into japan after 1945
after the americans started occupying
japan yeah
they essentially turned japan into a zoo
into a kind of disneyland where they can
go and you know have a holiday
so i think it would be somewhere around
that time if i'm not mistaken yeah that
baseball would have been introduced into
japan and
then the japanese ticket took it up i
suppose and adidas
now that you asked me is it adidas or is
it reebok
the the gopro culture right the the
unemployed youth in russia
they kind of wear those
jump suits traction tracks
which are
which are typically adidas i believe i
think that dates back to the 1980s the
olympics
in moscow were in 1980 i think that's
when adidas first came into
into russia
so most likely that is the beginning of
the association
of adidas
with russia and that's where the gopnik
culture probably first originates so it
looks like i was able to give you two
educated guesses how strange is that
anyhow
okay any other questions that i find
interesting
is there any such thing yeah listen
you want me to take your question you
have to make it interesting
uh
this is a question or a statement
malvika says
jordan peterson is well suited for
western philosophies only people try to
talk about his doctrines and beliefs in
the indian context that is quite undone
i agree with malvika
jordan peterson his entire world view is
completely abrahamic completely western
i find
overall he's
it's all about pain and struggle and and
the sadness and negativity
listen
he has some some interesting things to
say he's a very intelligent person a
very well dead person
but his overall outlook is all about
struggle and pain there is no joy in his
outlook
yeah it's a very abrahamic world with
ideas nothing against abrahamic work
culture or anything
whoever likes it feel free to like it
you have the right to like it i'm sure
that i
don't understand it completely yeah
the thing is i find his entire outlook
extremely negative and extremely
pessimistic
he doesn't believe in joy and happiness
yeah it's all about struggling and and
striving
and and
doing things even though there is no
happiness like that sort of thing you
know
so
whatever he whatever he says whatever
his his worldview is it is completely
western completely abrahamic it has no
meaning in the indian context
so i i overall
agree
with what malvika says here
and with that
we are at the end of today's session we
have crossed over so thank you very much
all of you for all the questions
always interesting always fun to take
your questions and let us keep doing
this we will keep doing this and i will
see you in the next episode
very soon
all right so until then take care
and i'll see you in the next video thank
you